<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Not so new, as true Being a verie necessarie caueat for all Christians to consider of. VVherein is truelie described the iniquitie of this present time, by occasion of our confused liuing: and iustlie approued the world to be neuer worse, by reason of our contagious leaudnes. By Charles Gibbon.</title>
            <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21014</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21014)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Not so new, as true Being a verie necessarie caueat for all Christians to consider of. VVherein is truelie described the iniquitie of this present time, by occasion of our confused liuing: and iustlie approued the world to be neuer worse, by reason of our contagious leaudnes. By Charles Gibbon.</title>
                  <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 14 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin, dvvelling in Paternoster rowe ouer against the signe of the Checker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title, B1r reads: A dialogicall discourse concerning the course of this world.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Not ſo new, as True.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being a verie neceſſarie Caueat for all</hi> Chriſtians to conſider of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein is truelie deſcribed the iniquitie of this</hi> preſent time, by occaſion of our confuſed liuing: And iuſtlie approued the world to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer worſe, by reaſon of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious leaudnes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Charles Gibbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The weaker the world is by reaſon of age, the more ſhall the euills bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed vpon them that dwell therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Eſdr. <hi>14.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> dwelling in Paternoſter rowe ouer againſt the ſigne of the Checker. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull, the Maior <hi>of the Burrough of</hi> Kings Linne, to his Aſſociates or Brethren, the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>of the ſame Towne: And to my</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie louing friends the Burgeſſes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie called the <hi>Eighteene</hi> of the ſame Aſſemblie.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>CHARLES GIBBON</hi> wiſheth proſperous health, <hi>and perpetuall happines.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Pollos</hi> being both eloquent and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the Scriptures, diſdained not to be further inſtructed in the way of the Lord by a poore Craftſman
<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24.</note>. Which example (Right Worſhipfull and my verie louing friends) as it commendeth <hi>Apollos</hi> for his pietie, ſo it incourageth me to proceed in hope of the like leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, albeit it condemneth many in theſe daies for their curioſitie: who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie meaſure men of learning by their liuing: valuing the ſinglenes of their gifts, by the ſimplenes of their eſtate: which is aſmuch as if they ſhould reiect the fine gold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lieth in the filthie ground: or the pure wine, for that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the homelie preſſe: or the pretious ſtone <hi>Draconites,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is drawne from the head of the Dragon. Nay more than that, for by how much ſpirituall gifts are to be preferred before temporall, ſo much the more are the compariſons intollerable, and the ſinne more execrable: and which indeed is a greater argument of inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, than humilitie: of prauitie, than pietie: and vndoubtedly is much repugnant to that ſame conformable courſe which S. <hi>Paule</hi> preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, who willeth, <hi>That in meekenes of mind euerie man esteeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better than himſelfe</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Phil 2.3.</note>. The ſame Apoſtle (I ſpeake it without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption) was well accepted of the Nobles at <hi>Berea</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note>, yet who more oppreſſed any way than he? they did not ballance the barenes of his abilitie, with the excellencie of his doctrine: but wee, or moſt of vs in theſe daies are ſo farre puffed vp with our knowledge, that we preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thoſe things which tend to our profite, by following our owne humors which turne to our hurt. And herein manie of vs which terme our ſelues Proteſtants, are iuſtlie to bee condemned with thoſe we <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>In all the kingdomes of</hi> Siria, Paleſtina, Arabia, Perſia, <hi>in all</hi> Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, <hi>and the Empire of</hi> Cappadocia, <hi>through the whole compaſſe of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, <hi>with</hi> Aegypt, <hi>and with</hi> Affrica <hi>alſo (vnleſſe amongſt the farre</hi> Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians <hi>ſome old ſteps of Chriſtianitie peraduenture do yet remaine),
<note place="margin">If the word of God decreaſe, ſinne muſt needs increaſe.</note> the Church of God hath not one foote of free land, but is all turned ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to infidelitie, or to captiuitie whatſoeuer pertaineth to him: and if</hi> Aſia <hi>and</hi> Affrica <hi>were onlie decaied, the decay were great, but yet the defection were not ſo vniuerſall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now of</hi> Europa <hi>a great part alſo is ſhronk fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church: all</hi> Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, <hi>with the Empire of</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>all</hi> Grecia, Epirus, Illiricum, <hi>&amp; now of late almoſt all the kingdome of</hi> Hungaria, <hi>with much of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, <hi>with lamentable ſlaughter of Chriſtian bloud is waſted and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Turkes, onlie a little angle in the Weſt parts yet remaining in ſome profeſsion of his name. Then ſeeing it is ſo, let vs not thinke our ſelues onlie happie by hauing the word, but more bleſſed if we obey it, and worſe than Infidels if wee abuſe it: let vs not increaſe, but ceaſe from ſinne, leaſt the Lord doo puniſh vs as he did thoſe places: ſeeing wee haue partlie experience of our apparant aduerſarie alreadie the Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>who ſtirreth vp his Biſhops to burne vs, his confederates to conſpire our destruction, ſetting Kings to deale cruellie againſt their ſubiects, and ſubiects to rebell diſloyallie againſt their Princes. Theſe practiſes may premoniſh vs to esteeme better of the word of God, if we haue any ſpark of grace: and our impendent deſtruction may inforce vs to repent, if wee haue any feare of his wrath, which God graunt,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>Charles Gibbon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>In this Booke is contained a fewe <hi>effectuall notes</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Concerning the latter day, and how farre our earthlie experience may extend in that ſecret.</p>
            <p>Of the danger of the good and bad together, and for what cauſe the wicked are to be cut off.</p>
            <p>Touching the true vſe of hoſpitalitie, and why it ought not to be reiected.</p>
            <p>For ſuch as haue ſatietie of riches, and how they ought to eſteeme and vſe them.</p>
            <p>Againſt ſuch as abridge the liberties of the poore, and what puniſhment is pronounced againſt them.</p>
            <p>Againſt rent raiſers, and the plagues that impend ouer their heads.</p>
            <p>Againſt Vſurers, and the hurt that commeth of their hard dealing.</p>
            <p>Whereby is approued the world to bee neuer worſe, by many probable arguments.</p>
            <p>Wherein is inſerted many neceſſarie inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt the reſt, for all ſorts to conſider of.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21014:4"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>earth and behold it was corrupt: for all fleſh had corrupt his way vpon earth</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 6.12.</note>. You ſhall finde how <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorha</hi> in the pride of their filthines were conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire: for it is written, <hi>the crie of Sodom and Gomorha was great, and their ſinne exceeding grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 18.20.</note>. Now, as this doth manifeſt the end to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, where the people be impenitent: ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning amendment (if a particular example may argue a generall preſumption) you ſhall reade, how the <hi>Niniuites</hi> in their aboundance of abomination, did repent and amend by the preaching of <hi>Ionah</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ionah 3.10.</note>. Such is the diuine prouidence of the almightie, that where he ſeeth anie care of reformation, he prolongeth the daies; where there is no hope of conuerſion, he proceedeth to deſtruction.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well; but I am perſwaded it will ſooner end than amend, and ſo much the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in conferring all ages together, by computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of yeares, this time approacheth to the end; by reuelation of prophecies, all things are apparant; by courſe of Scripture, all things are accompliſhed. Haue we not ſeen merueilous wonders in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens
<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 24. Luk 21. Mark. 13.</note>? ſtraunge mutations on the earth: Hath not rumors runne of warres, and Realme riſen againſt Realme? Haue wee not taſted of famine, been tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with plagues, and terrified with Earthquakes? Is there not at this day common murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall wreſting of the word, deriſion of Gods Miniſters, diuiſion betweene fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſonne? Hath not the Goſpell been prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the world
<note n="e" place="margin">Coloſſ 1 6.</note>? Is not that prophecie of <hi>Daniel</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21014:4"/>long ſince expired
<note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 12.12.</note>? Doth not Antichriſt play <hi>rex?</hi> Is there not a defect &amp; Apoſtacie from the faith
<note n="g" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>? yea what ſignes precede the end that haue not come to paſſe? or what may procure that heauie day of wrath that is wanting? The world is now woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with all corruption, as the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith: <hi>It lieth in wickednes</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">1. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>. The ſame cup of wine which the prophets ſpeake on, is dronke to the verie dregs of Gods indignation
<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 75.8. Iſay. 51.17. Iere. 25.15.</note>: the people are now nuſled in all iniquitie: and no doubt if the Lord ſhould looke downe from heauen, as he did in the daies of <hi>Dauid,</hi> he ſhould ſee, <hi>they are all gone out of the way and altogether become abominable, there is none that doth good, no not one</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 14 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. Yea they are growne ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, they ſlea their owne ſoules; ſo ſinfull, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get GOD; ſo ſecure, they feare no deſtruction; O carnall vanitie, O earthlie vilanie, O mortall miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: Inſomuch as the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of this confuſed wretchednes, would inforce our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe to ſhed teares, as he did for <hi>Iheruſalem</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Luk. 19.41.</note>, and ſhould make that terrible noiſe of the laſt Trompe to bee daylie ſounding in our eares, to awaken vs from our wickednes. And therefore,
<note place="margin">The prauitie of our liues is a preſumption of the end.</note> ſeeing it is with vs, as it was in the daies of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding euill, what ſhould we expect but a ſodaine end? As for amendment, it is doubtfull (vnles Gods mercie ſurmounteth): for the diuell beeing come downe amongſt vs, he hath great wrath: becauſe he knoweth his time is verie ſhort
<note n="m" place="margin">Apoc. 12.12</note>. Beſides, it is rare to ſee a rotten roote reuiue, or withered graſſe to waxe greene, or (as wee commonlie ſay) ſower drinke <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21014:5"/>
               <p> If the wiſedome of it bee meere follie before God
<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.20.</note>? who would applie his wits altogether to worldlines; ſeeing <hi>Paule</hi> iudged all things here no better worth than dung
<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note>, to win Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As concerning the latter day.</p>
               <p>If the Apoſtles ſaid aboue fifteene hundred yeres paſt, the day draweth neere
<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 10.25.</note>, and is at hand
<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 12.12. 1. Pet. 4.7.</note>; how nigh may wee now thinke it is? If the Lord hath deferred his comming, let vs not imagine (with thoſe mockers Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of) he hath forgot his promiſe; but let vs rather ſuppoſe his long ſuffering
<note n="f" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.15.</note> is ſaluation; who vſeth patience onlie to drawe vs to repentance: and therefore let vs not deſpiſe the riches of his bountifulnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, but call for grace in time, leaſt at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming we procure
<note n="g" place="margin">Rom 2.4.</note> our greater condemnation.</p>
               <p>As concerning the certeintie of the time.</p>
               <p>If Chriſt commeth vnawares as a theefe in the night, and in the houre we thinke not
<note n="h" place="margin">Matth. 24.44</note>, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie ought we to watch and pray continually leaſt he commeth ſodeinlie and finde vs ſleeping? It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs to take heed to our ſelues that our hearts bee not oppreſſed with ſurfetting, dronkennes, and ſuch like
<note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 21.34.</note>, but that we may haue alwaies an earneſt meditation of our end: for then (as <hi>Syrack</hi> ſaith) we ſhould not doo amiſſe
<note n="k" place="margin">Eccle 7.36.</note>. <hi>Oh that they were wiſe,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 32.29.</note> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>then they would vnderſtand this: they would conſider their latter end.</hi> So that it rather ſtands vs vpon to be in preparation for the end, being ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21014:5"/>than in diſputation of a matter,
<note place="margin">We ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer liue as we would daylie die.</note> being doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and as euerie day doth threaten our deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo let euerie one haue a feeling of his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and ſeeing the reward of ſinne is death
<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note>, the day of death vncerteine, and euerie mans death is his owne dome
<note n="n" place="margin">Eccle. 11.3.</note>, we ſhould daylie thinke our end to be imminent, and ſo by the feare of Gods puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, haue a care of repentance; leaſt diſpenſing leaudlie with the time, wee preſume vainlie of our ſelues, the diuell plaieth ſubtillie with our ſoules, and God plague vs ſodainlie for our ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>You miſtake my meaning altogether: for albeit I beleeue Chriſt will come to iudgement, and that ſhortlie;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>It is a great ſinne to enter into Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets.</hi> 2. Eſdr. 4.2.</note> yet I doo not preſume of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time of his comming certeinlie; that were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable before GOD, and not tollerable among men: but, as manie writers haue made much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this matter; ſo amongſt them, ſuch are moſt to be preferred that rather perſwade vs by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant proues of an imediat end, than thoſe which by palpable meanes, would prolong the time by prolixious arguments: the one doth put vs in mind to bee in a daylie preparation, with the fiue wiſe Virgins to meete the Bridegrome
<note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 25.4.</note>: the other doth feede vs with a vaine deluſion, as an occaſion to make vs followe that confuſed courſe of the leand ſeruant our Sauiour Chriſt deſcribeth
<note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 24 49</note>: that doth dehort vs from impietie, and drawe vs to amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; this doth flatter vs in ſecuritie, and mooue vs to all miſchiefe. To what end did the Apoſtles in their daies perſwade the people ſo often, the day of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21014:6"/>
               <speaker>Alpheus.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede the ſuperſtition in times paſt ſhould ſo pitie vs to remember, that it ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs to amendment, for it was ſo far from good conformitie that I pray God vtterly to confound it; notwithſtanding, when Idolatrie was moſt rifeſt, a faithfull congregation was reſident, euen as there hath alwaies been from the beginning; for GOD hath aſwell his elected as eiected in all places: they are but fewe in number, and therefore termed verie fitlie, a little flocke
<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 12.32.</note>: alluding to that ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>the way is narrowe that leadeth vnto life, and fewe there be that finde it</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 7.14.</note>. God had reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſome righteous amongſt the reprobate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Elias</hi> thought there was none left but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone
<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 11.4.</note>. We haue had experience of late daies, of godlie Martirs among the wicked malefactors, who like the Glazeworme gliſtered moſt brightlie in the night, or like the Lampe gaue moſt light in the darke, whoſe faith was tried as gold in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace;
<note place="margin">The godlie will rather die tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denie Chriſt.</note> who did rather chuſe to ſuffer manie trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in a good cauſe, than abide the terror of an ill conſcience; yea rather to indure the torments of fire, than ſubmit themſelues to the extremitie of their factions.
<note place="margin">Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> If you peruſe the Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, you ſhall finde how they yeelded their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies like faggots to the fire, rather than they would followe any ſottiſh filthines contrarie to their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere profeſsion;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>To ſuffer for the name of God is his onlie gift.</hi> Philip. 1.29.</note> being incouraged by that ſaying of S. <hi>Paule:</hi> If wee ſuffer with Chriſt, wee ſhall alſo raigne together with him: As contrariwiſe, if wee denie him hee will alſo denie vs
<note n="y" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.12.</note>. Remembring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21014:6"/>what our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Matth. 5.10.</note>: knowing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, that he which indureth to the end ſhall bee ſaued
<note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 24.13.</note> and obtaine a crowne of life
<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 2.10.</note>. But to the matter, as for the free libertie of the glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell amongſt vs (God maintaine it with her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie) for as ſhe doth vſe all the meanes that may bee to increaſe the light; ſo God knowes how manie there bee (which vpon a miſchiefe) would extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it: and as it was in the time of Poperie,
<note place="margin">If God be on our ſide, who can be against vs ſaith Paule.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuperſtition was generallie eſtabliſhed and allowed, and yet all did not affect or followe it, but ſome would rather ſuffer than do ſo: Euen ſo it is in theſe religious daies of ours, although Gods word be amongſt vs publikelie maintained;
<note place="margin">A priuie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt is worſe than a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe he ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be but luke-warme.</note> yet no doubt there are manie that priuilie miſlike it, as there bee ſome that openlie oppoſe themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Haue wee not had amongſt vs ſuch as terme themſelues the <hi>Familie of Loue, Ieſuites, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Priests,</hi> and ſuch like ſottiſh ſects?
<note place="margin">Theſe thinke there is a day comming, which they accompt their Iubile.</note> Is there not among vs at this day, opinatiue perſons, Papiſts, and ſuch like ſorts? What ſhould I ſay, I pray God it bee not verified by the people of England, as it was by the children of Iſrael, <hi>Though their number were as the ſand of the ſea, yet ſhall but a remnant be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 9 27. Eſay. 10.21.</note>. I feare me, the moſt, if their faith ſhould come to triall by fire, would keepe their bodies from the brands, they would (as wee commonlie ſay) rather turne than burne. A true Chriſtian is not knowne in peace, but in perſecution: <hi>All that will liue godlie in Chriſt</hi> (ſaith
<note n="d" place="margin">2. Tim 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi>) <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> Not when <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:21014:7"/>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe daies I muſt needes confeſſe bee dangerous
<note n="m" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.</note>, and it is come to paſſe as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe propheſied, that after his departing, grieuous woolues ſhould enter into his flocke
<note n="n" place="margin">Luk 10.3. Act. 20.29.</note>: no doubt there is now as hath been at all times, the good and bad together; as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, veſſells of honor and diſhonor
<note n="o" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.20.</note>: and no meruaile; for it is common to ſee the corne and cockle growe together on one ground; the flower and the weed in one gardaine; the bloſſome and the blaſt both on a tree. You ſhall reade in the Scriptures, that wheate and tares ſhall growe both together vntill harueſt,
<note place="margin">The wicked ſhall wander with the godlie vntill the end of the world.</note> that the ſheepe and the goates ſhall go together vntill the laſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and that the godlie and the wicked ſhall walke together vntill the end of the world. When the ſeruants would haue gathered the tares from the wheate, our Sauiour Chriſt would not ſuffer them, <hi>leaſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>while ye go about to gather the tares, ye plucke vp alſo with them the wheate: but let both growe together till harueſt</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 13.29</note>. So that of neceſsitie the wicked muſt remaine, becauſe it is impoſsible to roote them out, or verie dangerous to remooue them. Your next diſcourſe touching hypocriticall dealing, as it is a ſuppoſition vncertaine to mans cenſure; ſo being ſo tedious, I will ſay little to it; I deteſt ſuch as double in Religion, but I cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect any to be an hipocrite; and although we ought to abſtaine from all appearance of euill
<note n="q" place="margin">1. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.22</note>, yet wee muſt not iudge alwaies according
<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 7.24.</note> to appearance, eſpeciallie in this ſecret of the heart,
<note place="margin">Omne ſimile non eſt idem.</note> ſeeing it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſerued to God; neither may I iudge euill of my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21014:7"/>brethren, when I deeme none worſe than my ſelfe, conſidering God ſhall iudge vs all: but if there bee any ſuch as you ſet downe; this is moſt certaine, as euerie fatt doth ſtand of his owne bottome, ſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſinner, ſhall beare his owne burthen
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Galat 6.5.</note>; and as the tree lieth as it falleth, ſo ſhall he bee iudged as he dieth
<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 9 27.</note>. Beſides if the righteous ſcarſlie be ſaued
<note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.18.</note> (as it is fearefull to all ſinners) ſo how horrible wil it be for the hypocrite to appeare, whoſe portion is to ſuffer the extreameſt paines of hell
<note n="x" place="margin">Iob. 36.13.</note>. As for your concluſion, concerning the ſufferance of ſuch as haue libertie to doo well, and will not: Truelie ſuch is the good pitie of our Prince, that where heretofore ſome haue burned ſuch as were godlie, for a good cauſe; ſhe beares with ſuch as bee vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, for a further conſideration: not tendering their caſe, to their confuſion;
<note place="margin">A godlie prince exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in hope of amendment.</note> but intending a care of their conuerſion, ſtaying oftentimes where ſhe might ſtrike, in hope of amendment; yet ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſometime where ſhe muſt needes, for feare of a miſchiefe (Oh Princely patterne of patience, oh worthie mirror of mercie): Remembring alwaies to ſet good againſt euill, to beare with the weake, and to forbeare the froward a while, as vncertaine in what houre GOD may call ſuch into his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard
<note n="y" place="margin">Matth. 20.1. &amp;c.</note>, conſidering he is both miraculous and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull in his calling, who although he leaueth the wicked to their owne luſtes a time, he eftſoone doth conuert them to goodnes by his grace, as he did the Gentiles,
<note n="z" place="margin">Act 14 16.</note> that walked in their own waies; as he did the prodigall child,
<note n="a" place="margin">Luk 15 11.</note> that lauiſhed all he had <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:8"/>
                  <hi>conſequent</hi> (if they be not cut off) ouercome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>The companie of the good and bad to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as it is common, ſo I muſt needes confeſſe it is dangerous: and as ſuperſticious errors, hereſies, and ſuch like, are vtterlie to bee condemned; ſo in ſome ſort they are to bee admitted, as may appeare by that ſaying of S. <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians: There muſt be hereſies</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>amongst you, that they which are approued among you might bee knowne</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.19</note>. Not that hereſies and errors are to bee allowed or followed; but that by them the infallible trueth may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be diſcerned,
<note place="margin">Though error be admitted, it is not to be imitated.</note> and more eſteemed of the elect; for this is certaine, when contraries are oppoſite, the good hath his better appearance, euen as blacke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth beſt being drawne of a white border; ſo vertue is then moſt viſible when it is inuironed with vice; and what may more moue vs to regard the excellencie of the word of God,
<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of error is an inſtigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to goodnes in the godlie.</note> than to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs the enormitie that may inſue of error. God ſometimes to prooue his children will place them amongſt the wicked, to ſee whether they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their waies, as he did by the Iſraelites
<note n="q" place="margin">Iudg. 2.22.</note>; yet he doth it not to that end we ſhould incline to euil, or that he himſelfe is ignorant of the iſſue; but that he would haue it appeare to vs, he hath appoynted them as his inſtruments for the triall of our faith
<note n="r" place="margin">Deut. 13.3.</note>, and that by conſtant perſeuerance we ſhall obtaine a crowne of life
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Apoc 2.10. <hi>Al thoſe means that haue been offered to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime vs, ſhall come againſt vs to condemne vs.</hi>
                  </note>. But to the purpoſe, as for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, if neither the preaching of the word will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them, the pricke of their owne conſcience ſtirre them, the perſwaſion of the godlie moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21014:8"/>nor the patience of a good Magiſtrate amend them; no doubt, all theſe meanes will be a witnes of their owne miſerie
<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 18.19.</note>, and euerie houre will threatten their miſhap: for it is written, <hi>There ſhall be no end of plagues to the euill man, and his destruction ſhall riſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlie</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Prou 24.20.22.</note>. And therefore (as it is recorded in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation of <hi>Iohn</hi>) Let him that is vniuſt, bee vniuſt ſtill; that is filthie, be filthie ſtill; that is righteous, be righteous ſtill; that is holie, be holie ſtill: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ſaith Chriſt, I come ſhortlie, and my reward is with me to giue to euerie man according as his worke ſhall be
<note n="x" place="margin">Apoc. 22.11. <hi>Euerie one ſhal beare his owne burthen.</hi>
                  </note>. Then they ſhall find that the ſame ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die; that euerie one ſhal giue accompt of himſelfe, and that the reward of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes is hell fire. So, let vs neither enuie them
<note n="y" place="margin">Pro. 24.19.</note>, but vſe all the waies that may be to win them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs imitate them, but let euerie one of vs ſay with good <hi>Ioſhua, I and my houſhold will ſerue the Lord</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Ioſh 24.15. <hi>It is wiſedome to feare, but not to followe the worſt.</hi>
                  </note>. As for cutting them off for feare of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to forbeare a good deede for feare of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; and hee that feareth all inconueniences ſhall neuer doo his duetie: according to that ſaying of <hi>Salomon, He that obſerueth the winde, ſhall not ſowe, and he that regardeth the clowdes, ſhall not reape</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Eccle. 11.4.</note>. You produce manie reaſons for this matter, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are more prolixious to make argument, than probable to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the trueth, or appliable to your opinion:
<note place="margin">None may pleade againſt Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> for there is no carnall reaſon currant with God, neither muſt you pleade earthlie experience againſt his eternall prouidence: For albeit to our ſenſuall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there ſeemeth no hope or means of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:9"/>haue the foxes, yea the little foxes taken away
<note n="h" place="margin">Can. 2.15.</note>; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting indeed, that although the oldeſt did moſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, yet the yongeſt did ſome hurt, and were not to bee ſuffered, leaſt they diſturbe, or (by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) deſtroy the vine:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The declai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Iuſtice increaſeth euil.</hi> Eccle. 8.11.</note> whereby we may learne to remoue the meanes of miſchiefe, and to cut off the cauſes of corruption in the beginning, eſpeciallie in theſe perilous daies, conſidering the readie inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manie to euill
<note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.</note>: for ſuch is the inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of error and ſuch like, that it will ſpread like the vine, if it bee not cut off; ſcatter like the ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beware of the leauen of the Phariſies.</hi> Mark. 8.15.</note> if it be not ſtaid; and mount like the palme, if it be permitted: and therefore in time it is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented. As for that ſame place of S. <hi>Paule</hi> you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce touching the admiſsion of hereſies amongſt the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 21.19</note>; truelie it is to no purpoſe to proue the opinion you hold: for the ſame Apoſtle (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the great preiudice might come by ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious members) willed <hi>Titus to reiect him that is an heretike, after once or twiſe admonition: knowing that he that is ſuch, is peruerted, and ſinneth being damned of his owne ſelfe</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Tit. 3.10.11.</note>. And what ſhould moue anie to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine or meddle with ſuch, ſeeing their properties (deſcribed by an ancient father) are ſo peſtiferous; they are ſubtill like foxes, biting like doggs, proud like Lyons
<note n="m" place="margin">Barnard.</note>? And as for the reſt of your matter, ſeeing it is nothing materiall to the purpoſe, I will (for breuitie ſake) omit to anſwere it: So that all things being ſeriouſlie conſidered (according to my former aſſertion) I can ſee no cauſe why ſuch (as we haue argued of) ſhould be continued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21014:9"/>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>If you bee ignorant of that you ſhould knowe, you muſt not be obſtinate where you may learne; you harpe all vppon one ſtring, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it pleaſe your ſelfe, it yeeldes no perfect ſound: what ſhould wee ſo ſingularlie accompt of our ſelues, ſeeing (as the Apoſtle ſaith) in manie things we ſinne al
<note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note>? Or what ſhould we ſo ſtrickt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deale with others that cannot doo well, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring when we haue all done what wee can, yet the beſt is but an vnprofitable ſeruant
<note n="o" place="margin">Luk 17.14.</note>? And ſurelie if we did diſcend narrowlie into our ſelues, it would appeare we are ſo blind, we cannot ſee the beames in our owne eyes, though we be ſo buſie to meddle with motes in others:
<note place="margin">The looſenes of our liues make the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate.</note> for vndoubtedly there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that giueth greater liberty of offence to thoſe which wee terme Papiſts, and ſuch like, than the looſenes of our liues, which profeſſe our ſelues to be Proteſtants: If our conuerſation were confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to our profeſsion, it could not but drawe them to a more deſire of amendment. It was this that prouoked <hi>Peter</hi> to perſwade the wiues to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie and ſubiection, that others may be wonne by their conuerſation which obey not the word
<note n="p" place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>; and for this cauſe there is required in vs a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, that wee may giue no euill occaſion anie way to the aduerſarie
<note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet. 2 12.</note>. What profiteth proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of great learning, where there followeth no forwardnes in our liuing.
<note place="margin">It is proper to manie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe well, but giuen to fewe to followe it</note> It is expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a good Chriſtian, not onlie to bee an open profeſſor of the word of God, but alſo to be a godlie patterne by his life and deedes. Hereof ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:10"/>Let ter tollerate him that trips in the true knowledge of God, than him that vtterlie denies his Godhead
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>If any man loue not the Lord Ieſus Christ let him be had in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration.</hi> Mara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natha. 1. Cor. 16 22.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thoſe that ſwarue from the word of God cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed.</hi> Prou. 15.10. &amp;c.</p>
                  </note>: if we hang ſuch as imbeaſell our goods, ſhall we har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor ſuch as impaire his glorie? ſhall we prefer tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, more then his eternall Maieſtie? No no, all libertie is too little where there is hope of recouetie; anie, is too much where the caſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable. Therefore to conclude, as thoſe which are tractable to be taught, &amp; conformable to good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are to bee continued, ſo ſuch as ſet abroach groſſe importable errors, and obſtinatlie perſeuer, are to be cut off, leaſt others by their example be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated to euill: for better it were to decide one me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, than indanger the whole body. And this is tollerable by the warrant of Gods word, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by theſe directions
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Minister of God beareth not the ſworde for nought: but to take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on him that doth euill.</hi> Rom. 13.4.</note>. <hi>That man that will doo preſumptuouſly not harkening vnto the Prieſt that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before the Lord thy God to miniſter there, or vnto the Iudge, that man ſhall die and thou ſhalt take away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from Iſraell; ſo all the people ſhall heare and feare and doo no more</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Deut 17.12.13.</note>. And hereto agreeth that godly act which is recorded by <hi>Ezra. Whoſoeuer will not do the Lawe of God, and the Kings Lawe, let him haue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without delay whether it bee vnto death, or to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or to confiſcation of goods, or to impriſonment</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ezra. 7.26.</note>. I could dilate the confirmation hereof by manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approbations to the like effect, but ſeeing it is alreadie ſufficien the proued: it were not ſo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous for me to inſert, as it wil be friuolous for you to replie; and ſo I leaue it to your conſideration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Albeit I was ſomewhat willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21014:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the weake, I was neuer ſo forward to iuſtifie the wicked, or ſo fooliſh, to ſtand in my owne conceit: for as the word of God is the perfect touch of all trueth,
<note place="margin">Mens reaſons are but tickle, but the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten trueth can neuer ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</note> ſo I euen refer my reaſons to that rule, &amp; at this time ſubmit my ſelf to your ſayings; not for want of matter to make further obiection, but becauſe it is altogether impertinent to proue your firſt opinion, &amp; therfore I pray ſhew me what moues you to ſay the world was neuer worſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alreadie partlie approued to the contrarie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray tell me, what are become of theſe auncient Monuments, ſtatelie Monaſteries, and huge buildings that were wont to bee, where the poore might haue continuall acceſſe for reliefe, and the ſtranger free reſort for ſuccor? are theſe not defaced? but their free ſtones haue bewtified moſt of our faire buildings
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were not taken away out of Iſrael, yet the heart of Aſa was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect all his daies.</hi> 2. Chro. 14.17. <hi>We feede the poore with faire ſhowes in ſteede of foode.</hi>
                  </note>. Where are become all the reuenewes and lands that belonged to them, which (by report) were large? are not the better ſort inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with their liuings? Yea no doubt (ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet apart) this ſeaſon were incomparable to it. We haue now ſumptuous houſes, but ſlender hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallitie: for all the ſmoke comes out of one chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; great ſubſtance, but ſmall charitie, for euerie one is for himſelfe; now hoſpitalitie is turned to prodigalitie, all bountie to brauerie: then was good faith amongſt all folkes;
<note place="margin">The time hath been, when more words were vſed tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> writings, and yet better dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling than at theſe daies.</note> trueth went by tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, their dealing was ſoo ſimple, now nothing will ſerue, men are ſo ſubtill: then was good neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood without nicenes, now giuen ouer for griple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; or little vſed without curiouſnes: all things then <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:11"/>
                  <hi>gather thy grapes cleane after thee, but they ſhall bee for the ſtranger, fatherles and widowe, that the Lord thy God may bleſſe thee in all the works of thy hand</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Deut. 24.19.20.21.</note>. Such was the good prouidence of God, that ſomewhat ſhould be left by the way of reliefe to the diſtreſſed: but in theſe daies we are growne ſo hard, that wee neither leaue ſheaues, rakings, nay hardly gleanings for the poore to gather: and as for fruite, many keep them till they rot, and giue them to hogs, rather when they are good, impart them to the poore. If hoſpitalitie were not neceſſarie, why did the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle put the Romaines in minde to giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to it
<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 12.13.</note>? Or admoniſh the Hebrewes not to be forgetfull of it
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Hebr. 13.2.</note>? Or exhort vs to be harberous one to another without grudging
<note n="t" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.9.</note>? If hoſpitalitie bee hurtfull, why haue thoſe proſpered that haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it, as <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; <hi>Lot,</hi> who in ſhape of men receiued Angels into their houſes
<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 18.2.3.</note>? As the <hi>Shunam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,</hi> who by intertayning <hi>Eliſha,</hi> according to hir deſire had a ſonne
<note n="x" place="margin">2. King. 4.14</note>? If hoſpitalitie were not good, why are thoſe plagued that pretermit it, as <hi>Nabal,</hi> who for the hardnes of his heart to <hi>Dauid</hi> in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and for the vnthankfulnes of his deliuerie being in great danger, the Lord abridged his daies
<note n="y" place="margin">1. Sam. 25.38</note>? As the rich man, who not tendring <hi>Lazarus</hi> extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, was tormented with intollerable paines in hell
<note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note>?</p>
               <p>What mooued our Sauiour Chriſt to ſay, <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gaue me no meate: I was aſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ye tooke me not in: I was naked, and ye clothed me not: ſicke, and in priſon, and ye viſited me not, &amp;c.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21014:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Verelie I ſay vnto you, in as much as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me: depart from me ye curſed into euerlaſling fire</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Math 25.41. &amp;c.</note>. Surelie not that wee ſhould preſume our ſaluation depends vpon works or merites; but that we ſhould learne to liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of charitie, and not ſo lightly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of hoſpitalitie. It was this that made <hi>Iob</hi> in his innocencie to burſt foorth and ſay; <hi>If I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the poore of their deſire,
<note place="margin">The true vſe of hoſpitalitie, is to make proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the poore.</note> or haue cauſed the eyes of the widowe to faile, or haue eaten my morſels alone, and the fatherles haue not cate thereof: If I haue ſeene anie periſh for want of clothing, or anie poore without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering; If his loynes haue not bleſſed me becauſe he was warmed with the fleece of my ſheepe; If I haue lift vp my hand againſt the fatherles, when I ſawe I might helpe him in the gate, let my arme fall from my ſhoulder and be broken from the bone</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 31.16. &amp;c.</note>. We haue ſuch indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, that will make bounteous fare for their betters; ſumptuous feaſtes for their friends; coſtlie cheere for their kindred, and yet will ſcarſe afford a little bread or broth to the poore;
<note place="margin">Hoſpitalitie conſists not in ſuperfluitie, or in preparation of great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for our owne diots.</note> is not this (as we terme it) baſting the fat hogge, where they may bee acquited with like coſt and curteſie. Call you this hoſpitalitie; then <hi>Diues</hi> did well, for he fared delitiouſlie; but if we take his courſe, wee ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come in heauen. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs the true vſe of hoſpitalitie: <hi>When thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt a feast</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>call the poore, the maimed, the lame, and the blind, and thou ſhalt bee bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot recompence thee</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Luke. 14.13.</note>. Hereto agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that ſame notable ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Eſaias,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:12"/>he delt by <hi>Iob,</hi> who hauing aboundance of wealth, they were ſodainlie taken away
<note n="q" place="margin">Iob. 1.12.</note>. What follie to be a drudge for them? Why? <hi>Salomon</hi> willeth vs to trauaile not much to be rich
<note n="r" place="margin">Pro. 23.4.</note>, but to ceaſe from our wiſedome: for indeed as wee come naked out of our mothers wombe, ſo we ſhal returne: and (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) carrie nothing away when wee die
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 49.17.</note>. What felicitie to gather them? Why? they can neither prolong our life in this world
<note n="t" place="margin">Luke 12 15.</note>, or auaile vs in the day of wrath
<note n="u" place="margin">Prou. 11.4.</note>. What fearefulnes to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Why? <hi>It is eaſier for a Camel to go through a needles eie, than for the rich man to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Matt. 19 24.</note>. <hi>Go to now ye rich men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames) weepe and houle for the miſeries ſhall come vpon you</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Iam. 5.1.</note>. Thus if men had aſmuch grace as they haue goods, or were as mindfull of their ſaluation, as their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they would neither be ſo griple in gathering, ſo hard in withholding, or ſo loath in leauing this worldlie wealth; but ſo accompt of them, to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe them as the gift of God; to diſpoſe them as his ſtewards,
<note place="margin">Chriſtians ſhould thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their riches.</note> and to impart them as Chriſtians: So by this meanes the poore ſhould bee more reſpected, the Common wealth more increaſed, &amp; this time not ſo iuſtly condemned.
<note place="margin">Againſt ſuch as vſe incroch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the poore.</note> Is there not ſuch amongſt vs, as do inlarge their owne liuings, by incroching vpon the poore, by eating vp their lands, in buying houſes ouer their heads, by abridging their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and taking away their Commons? I feare me, if the complaints of the poore were fauourablie pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, their eſtate would appeare lamentable; and if the extremitie of the rich were exactlie ſearched,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21014:12"/>their dealings would proue intollerable. What a thing is this,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſtone ſhall crie out of the wall, and the beame out of the Timber ſhall anſwere it.</hi> Hab. 2.11.</note> that thoſe which haue the whole world at will to walke in, ſhould ſo hardlie allowe their poore brethren the bare aire to breathe in. Theſe are they whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh on, <hi>There is a generation</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whoſe teeth are as ſwords, and their chawes as kniues to eate vp the afflicted out of the earth, and the poore from among men</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Prou. 30.14.</note>. I meruaile what ſhould moue men to be ſo miſerable in their dealings, ſeeing it is ſo reproueable by the word of God? Are the Scriptures written onlie for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note>, and ſhall we contemne it in our liuing? Is it ſufficient for vs to talke, and not to walke well; to profeſſe much, and follow nothing? Doth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſay in vaine, <hi>Wo vnto them that ioyne houſe to houſe, and lay field to field, that there bee no place, that ye may bee placed by your ſelues in the middes of the earth</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Eſay. 5.8.</note>. Doth the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſpeake to no purpoſe, <hi>Wo vnto him that buildeth his houſe by vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and his chambers without equitie</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Iere. 22.13.</note>. Is it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to no end, <hi>Curſed is he that remoueth his neighbours marke, and all the people ſhall ſay, Amen</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 27.19.</note> Is it fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told in <hi>Hoſea</hi> to no effect, <hi>The Princes of Iudah were like them that remoue the bound: therefore will I powre out my wrath vpon them like water</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Hoſea 5.10. <hi>Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to a troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſcience.</hi>
                  </note>. Oh horrible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations for a hard conſcience? Oh fearefull iudgement for wicked creatures? What conqueſt is it to ouercome the poore, ſeeing it will bee the cauſe of your owne confuſion: <hi>For</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>the Lord will defend their cauſe, and ſpoyle the ſoule of thoſe that ſpoyle them</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Prou. 22.23.</note>. What
<pb facs="tcp:21014:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay, <hi>He that ſheweth no mercie, ſhall haue merciles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Iacob. 2.13.</note>. Doth not our Sauiour Chriſt ſay, <hi>Such meaſure as you mete ſhall be met to you againe</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Marc. 18.28. &amp;c.</note>. Haue you not example of the Seruant, who being pitied of the King his maſter, becauſe he ſhewed no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to his fellowe that was in his daunger, he was caſt into priſon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rehoboam op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple grieuouſlie, but the Lord did puniſh him by the loſse of the tenth part of his Realme.</hi> 1. King. 12. 2. Chro. 12.</note> there to remaine vntill he had paid the vttermoſt penie to his maſter? But if you had as forward wills to practiſe that is good, as you haue flattering reaſons to perſwade you to your hurt, you would neither prouoke God of malice, when you ſee what is written, or oppreſſe the poore by might, when you knowe you do wrong, or hate him that reproues you, when you heare he doth well.</p>
               <p>Is there not amongſt vs one neighbour that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieth another,
<note place="margin">For ſuch as bee contentious &amp; take delight in lawing.</note> that will wrangle for a word, that will go to lawe (as we commonlie ſay) for a ſtraw? Truelie there was neuer more impietie amongſt Pagans, then there is now contention amongſt Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">Many ſpend their money vpon malice, without regard of the goodnes of the matter.</note> who often times wilfullie will ſpend their monie waſtfullie, lauiſhing more vpon furie in a matter of no importance, than they gathered together before with great pains, giuing that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the Lawyer, that they haue gotten hardlie by their labour:
<note place="margin">Goods are the gift of God, but ſedition is the ſeede of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</note> Be theſe Chriſtians? Then they are more of ſpight, than the ſpirit. Are they neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? then they are more neere than neceſſarie: Be they men? then they are more wilful than wiſe: theſe are they that grutch to giue a penie to a poore Lazar, but they will not ſticke to beſtowe a pound
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21014:13"/>vpon the Lawyer: but when the ſting of their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes begin to bee ſtaid,
<note place="margin">The lawe is made, not to cauſe, but to keepe men from contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſcord.</note> and the ſwelling of their purſes doo ſomewhat aſſwage, then they leaue the lawe againſt their wills, and lament their ouerſight to their ſhame, ſuſtaining afterward great loſſe to their griefe, which before made the Lawyers to laugh with their gaines,
<note place="margin">Lawyers are neceſſary to pleade for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of trueth, but needeles, if they procure ſuites for their owne profits.</note> and then commonlie they fall from all reaſon to rage, exclaiming againſt the lawe without cauſe, when they ſhould condemne their owne leaudnes, which was the cauſe: they doo not conſider at the firſt what counſell S. <hi>Paule</hi> gaue to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> when they were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious: <hi>Is it ſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there is not a wiſe man amongſt you? no not one that can iudge betweene his brethren? Now therefore there is altogether infirmitie in you, in that ye go to lawe one with another: why rather ſuffer ye not wrong? why rather ſustaine ye not harme</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.5, 7. &amp;c.</note>? but at the laſt (yea too late) when all or much is waſted, then the Apoſtle can perſwade them to compromit matters,
<note place="margin">No wiſdome will perſwade the wilful in time.</note> and bring them to abide the arbitrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their brethren. Oh fooliſh furie of man, that cannot bridle the luſt of his mind, without loſſe of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and permit ſome iniurie with patience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out commenſing ſuit to his greater ſorrowe.
<note place="margin">We ought to ouercome euill with good with out rendring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill for euill.</note> Theſe are none of thoſe (whome our Sauiour Chriſt counſelleth) that will part from the cloake with the coate, rather then they will ſue; or turne the cheeke to take another blow, rather than they will ſtriue; or bliſſe where they curſe, rather than they wil ſuffer
<note n="q" place="margin">Matth 5.39. &amp;c.</note>: they can hardly do as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſigne his right, than contend with <hi>Let</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 13.8, 9.</note>: but they
<pb facs="tcp:21014:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>proſper? No, for although you haue no will to do well your ſelfe, you ſhall leaue them to ſuch as ſhall better beſtowe them; according as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that increaſeth his riches by vſurie and intereſt, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him that will be mercifull to the poore</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Prou 28.8. <hi>None may take lawfullie by lending one penny of profit.</hi>
                  </note>. What warrant haue you by the word of God to take anie lucre by lending; but rather a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the contrarie, <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue to vſurie to thy brother, as vſurie of monie, vſurie of meate, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of anie thing that is put to vſurie</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 23.19. leuit. 25.37.</note>. What ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel: He that hath giuen forth vpon vſurie, or taken increaſe, he ſhall not liue</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 18.13.</note>. Hereof ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> on the contrarie, <hi>He that giueth not his monie vnto v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, nor taketh reward againſt the innocent, ſhall neuer be moued</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 15.5.</note>. But theſe doo not care for the ſayings of the Scripture,
<note place="margin">Suauiseſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor lucri: Sed extremus eſt dolor infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</note> which do but grieue them: they are ſo carried with the ſauour of gaine, which is ſo ſweete to them, who as they repoſe all their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this life, ſo they haue no reſpect in their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or any feeling of the felicitie to come. As for the reſt of the ſinnes that raigne amongſt vs, becauſe they bee manie, I will omit: for it would require a large volume to expreſſe euerie vice; but let this ſuffice, there is no ſinne ſo hainous to repeate, ſo horrible to enterpriſe, or ſo abhominable before God, but at this day is amongſt vs as rife, as if the diuell bare the banner; as common, as though wee had no ſoules to ſaue; as careles, as though there were no God to reuenge: So that I may lawfullie affirme my firſt ſpeach, the world was neuer worſe than now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21014:14"/>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Your long diſcourſe diſcouereth manie a ſinne, which although they be common amongſt vs,
<note place="margin">All people haue their imperſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiont.</note> yet it is no conſequent occaſion to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne this time onlie; becauſe the world hath alwaies been bewitched with ſuch wickednes, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt predeceſſor, as permanent to all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: there is none exempted from ſinne; <hi>Lot, Dauid, Salomon,</hi> yea al our forefathers had their infirmities: there is no fire made of wood, but hath ſmoke; nor any man made of fleſh, but hath his faults: as the wiſeman writeth, <hi>There is no man iuſt on the earth that doth good and ſinneth not</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>: for if wee were able to refraine that wee ought, and willing to followe that we ſhould, wee might rather bee canonized for Saints, than condemned for ſinners: but there is ſuch a continuall combat betweene the fleſh &amp; the ſpirit
<note n="h" place="margin">Iacob. 4.1.</note>, that when wee haue a motion to do good, it withdraweth vs; and when wee haue a prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to euill, it putteth vs forward; according as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weake</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Matth. 26.4.</note>. It was this that made <hi>Paule</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and ſay, <hi>I allowe not that which I do; for that I would, that do I not; but what I hate, that do I</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Rom 7.19.</note>. And therefore it is no meruaile that we bee ſo inclined to euill in theſe daies, ſeeing the Apoſtles
<note n="l" place="margin">Matt. 26.74.</note>, nay the Prophets
<note n="m" place="margin">2. Sam. 11.2. &amp;c.</note>, yea the Patriarkes themſelues
<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 19.30.</note> haue been ſurpreſſed with ſinne, and that moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riblie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>I remember S. <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Barnard.</note> 
                  <hi>That the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of our weakenes, the ignorance of our wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the excuſing of our wickednes, and the perſeuering in</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21014:15"/>freelie? Is there not learned Diuines to expound it effectuallie? zealous preachers to inſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple continuallie?
<note place="margin">Where there is no will to doo well, Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſites are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</note> Yea, if anie people were euer cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by outward ſignes of Gods goodnes, it is we in England; who haue had all the meanes that may be to reclaime vs, being wicked; and to continue vs, doing well; that although our vntowardnes would not ſuffer vs, the time hath been ſufficient to haue taught vs: but no doubt euerie one knowes his duetie, though he doth it not; knows euill from good, though he eſchew it not: And therefore the verie Turkes, Infidels, and all the reſt of the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers ſhall riſe againſt vs at the latter day: for no doubt if they had taſted the ſweete treaſure of the word ſo long time as wee haue done,
<note place="margin">Heathen ſhall condemne Christians for the abuſe of Gods benefites.</note> they would ere this day haue brought foorth better fruites of their profeſsion in their liues and conuerſation, to our vtter ſhame and confuſion. So that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the whole courſe of the Scripture will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot yet heare any reaſon that ſhould inforce you to continue your former ſpeach, much leſſe perceiue any cauſe ſhould confirme it to bee true: for I am ſure we all acknowledge one God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo doo the diuels, and they feare and
<note n="u" place="margin">Iacob. 2.19.</note> tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble: but it is not ſufficient for vs to ſay we know God, vnleſſe wee keepe his commandements
<note n="x" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.4.</note>: for ſuch a one (the Apoſtle ſaith) is a lier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>There is not one can keepe the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements perfectlie in all poynts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>Yet we muſt not omit the meanes to come
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21014:15"/>as nigh as wee may: beſides,
<note place="margin">Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes is ours by imputation.</note> as Chriſt hath perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs, ſo he hath ſomewhat mitigated the hardnes thereof: <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my yoke is eaſie
<note n="y" place="margin">Matth. 11.30 1. Ioh. 5.3.</note>, and my burden light.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>We all like Chriſtians ſerue GOD, and call vpon his name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo doo the diuels likewiſe: for they ſerue god as his inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to do his good pleſure,
<note n="z" place="margin">Iob. 1.12.</note> and can call vpon him earneſtlie for a leaud prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<note n="a" place="margin">Mark. 5.10.</note>; but it is required of vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we call vpon his name; not to continue in euill, (as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith) <hi>Let euerie one that call vpon his name</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19</note> 
                  <hi>depart from iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> but to do his will reuealed in his word. Hereof ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Not euerie one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 7.21,</note>, <hi>but he that doth the will of my father which is in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>We frequent ſermons continuallie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>But what doth that preuaile,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>We ought ſo to heare the word as we may obey it, or els we doo but abuſe it.</hi> Eze. 33.31 &amp;c</note> vnleſſe wee conforme our ſelues by them? The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The hearers of the lawe are not righteous before God, but the doers of the lawe ſhall be iuſtified</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 2.13.</note>. And to this may fitlie be annexed that ſame ſaying of S. <hi>Iames, He that heareth the word and doth it not, is like vnto a man that beholdeth his naturall face in a glaſſe</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Iacob. 1.22.</note>: <hi>for when he hath conſidered himſelfe he goes his way, and forgetteth immediatlie what manner of one he was.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, that <hi>he is bleſſed</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 11.23.</note> 
                  <hi>that heareth the word and keepeth it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>We haue al great knowledge in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as may be, &amp; ſo much; that euerie one thinks himſelfe apter to teach than to learne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:21014:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe deſcribeth by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luk. 12.47.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Whatſoeuer I ſay, I perceiue you conſter it to the contrarie; which ſeeing it is ſo, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubmit my ſelfe to your cenſure, ſo it be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, than proceed ſtill in argument, if it were ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous: and therefore I pray in fewe words ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue your firſt ſpeach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>I could inferre further matter to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; but that which is alreadie ſaid is ſufficient to approoue it to bee true, if it be well conſidered, and may perſwade you to beleeue it, if you bee not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate; both for the free paſſage wee haue had of the word manie yeares without reſtraint; the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed peace wee haue enioyed in this land long time without trouble; and the little profite we haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to our ſelues, by reaſon of the benefite of both; where in times paſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The moe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon ante people, the more doth their ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and abuſe deſerue to bee puniſhed.</hi> Luk. 10.14. &amp;c. Pſal. 99 8. &amp;c.</note> the word was diſturbed with ſuperſtition, the land was incombred with perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that the people could not come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of true religion, in reſpect of the iniquitie of the time. And therefore, if they ſhall be beaten with fewe ſtripes, which were allowed no libertie to learne publiquelie; or at the leaſt, wanted the waies to win them to it, as we haue had continually, how manie ſtripes are wee worthie of, that are worſe than they, and yet haue had all the meanes that may be to amend vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Although I cannot but ſigh to ſee that which is euill, I muſt not let to ſay that which is true: for now I am fullie reſolued the world was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21014:16"/>neuer worſe, eſpeciallie with vs, who haue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie abuſed the benefite of Gods word, conſidering the innumerable ſinnes that raigne ſo rife in al ſorts of people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>Then, ſeeing we are a people as wicked, as they of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorha,</hi> and it is a ſeaſon as ſinfull, as it was in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> wee muſt not thinke (as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) the Lord will ſpare vs, more than thoſe
<note n="t" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.6.</note> whom he hath made en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt if we do not preſentlie repent we ſhall ſo prouoke the Lord, that in ſtead of peace he will procure vs trouble, and cauſe him (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it is written) to ſet his face againſt vs
<note n="u" place="margin">Leuit. 26.17.</note>, yea and ſuffer ſuch as hate vs to raigne ouer vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, more than that, if wee ſtill abuſe his bleſſed word, let vs take heed leaſt that ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie againſt Iſrael, bee verified in England; that the Lord ſend vs not a famine of bread, nor a thirſt for water; but a famine of hearing
<note n="x" place="margin">Amos. 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> his word, which God defend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord ſo do, and graunt that his fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſpirit may ſo thawe our froſen hearts, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to the ſight of our ſinnes, wee may bee ſorie for the ſame, and ſo afterward leade our liues in holines and righteouſnes before him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Nican.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing we haue waded thus farre, let vs proceed a little further: for me thinkes we cannot be better occupied, than to ſpend the time in godlie talk, &amp; to employe our pains to the profite of others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:21014:17"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> waies on earth; for the faſhion of it goeth away
<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31.</note>. If God hath appointed that all muſt once die
<note n="f" place="margin">Hebr. 9.27.</note> let vs not refuſe to ſuffer for the teſtimonie of a good conſcience; for as it is the onlie gift of God, ſo it is giuen but to a fewe
<note n="g" place="margin">Philip. 1.29.</note>; but bleſſed are thoſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it
<note n="h" place="margin">Matth. 5.10.</note>. Though the world bee waucring, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,
<note place="margin">It is required of vs ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite whileſt we poſſeſſe the word, as wee may perſiſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth God to proue vs for the ſame.</note> though ſome bee infected, yet all bee not affected to ſuperſtition; but manie are ſo farre from following it they vtterlie defie it. If the world be ſo waiward as you ſay, let not our mindes bee as mutable; but in theſe <hi>Alcyon</hi> daies let vs learne to lay a good foundation for our faith, that wee may gather ſuch godlie conſolation in time of peace, as may confirme our conſtancie againſt the daies of perſecution: for true it is the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>All that liue godlie in</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt ſhall ſuffer perſecution:</hi> and this is moſt certaine, the world will increaſe in euill
<note n="k" place="margin">2. Eſd. 14.16</note> as it doth in age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
               <p>We haue not ſaid anie thing but that is tollerable by the word of GOD, and profitable to manie, eſpeciallie to the well diſpoſed, who will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it, though the froward miſlike it. As we haue touched the Papiſts in friendly manner, ſo we haue not ouerſlipped our ſelues in flattering ſort: for both, nay all of vs are euill inclined, and therefore none of vs but may bee admoniſhed, yea and the beſt of vs amended. We haue not buſied our ſelues (as ſome do of late ſetting forth) in preſuming to meddle in manie matters that are vnmeete (who thinking to get credite by ſhewing a great gloſe by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21014:17"/>their curious arte, doo nothing els but reape re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach by their preſumptuous attempts, whoſe grace is altogether in diſgracing others); but wee haue conferred of ſuch matter as concernes the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie of the time, the beating downe of ſinne, and the aduancing of Gods glorie. And therefore leaſt wee bee counted to occupie our ſelues (as they did) more buſilie than wiſelie, wee will here abruptlie end till our next meeting, and then as occaſion ſhalbe miniſtred, we wil vſe further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. In the meane time I thank you for your companie, and commit you to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
